Guide to the Virginia Gardner Papers TAM 100
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Virginia Gardner Papers
1922-1990
TAM 100
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
12.0 linear feet (12 boxes)
Virginia Gardner (1904-1992) was a journalist, Communist, and biographer of Louise Bryant. She worked at several midwestern newspapers before joining the Chicago Tribune in 1930. Around 1937, she joined the Communist Party and was fired from the Tribune for her union activism in 1940. She then went to work for the Women's Division of the Democratic National Committee in New York and was briefly Executive Secretary of the American Council on Soviet Relations in Washington D.C.. She was active in the Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges, and wrote for the Federated Press(a labor news service), The New Masses, Peoples World(the CPUSA West Coast newspaper) in Los Angeles and the Daily Worker in New York where she covered the Rosenberg case in 1953. Gardner wrote The Rosenberg Story in 1954 and Friend and Lover, a Louise Bryant biography in 1982. Gardner died in 1992. The collection includes her correspondence, documentation of her political activities, research materials, manuscripts, autobiographical materials and articles.
Gardner, Virginia.
Provenance
This collection was donated by John Marberry, son of Virginia Gardner, on June 21, 1990.
Access Restrictions
There may be some restrictions on the use of the collection.
Historical/Biographical Note
Virginia Gardner (1904-1992) was a journalist, a communist, and biographer of Louise Bryant. She was raised in Fort Smith, Arkansas graduated with a B.A. in journalism from the University of Missouri in 1924, then worked at several Midwestern newspapers before joining the Chicago Tribune in 1930. Gardner gradually became a radical, joined the Communist Party c.1937, led the small Newspaper Guild group at the Tribune, and was fired for her union activism in March, 1940.
Blacklisted in Chicago, she moved to New York where she worked with the Women's Division of the Democratic National Committee. After her divorce from journalist Marion (Red) Marberry, Gardner moved to Washington, DC in 1942, and was briefly Executive Secretary of the American Council on Soviet Relations. Between 1940 and 1942 Virginia Gardner was active as a member of the Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges, serving as its Executive Secretary in 1941. From 1942-1943 she worked for the Federated Press (a labor news service), resigning over its unwillingness to criticize John L. Lewis. Gardner next worked for the New Masses, resigning in 1947 when it became a monthly.
She moved to Los Angeles, working for the Peoples World(the CPUSA West Coast newspaper) until her dismissal in 1951, and was then briefly employed at a meat packing plant. In 1952 Gardner moved to New York where, again, her first job was at a meat plant in Jamaica, Queens, before being employed by the Daily Worker where she covered the Rosenberg case in 1953, and later wrote The Rosenberg Story, which was published in 1954. In 1959 Virginia Gardner left the Worker, and between 1960 and 1962 worked as a medical writer. From 1963 to 1971 she worked as editorial assistant to Corliss Lamont. Her Louise Bryant biography was published in 1982. Soon afterwards she began working on her own autobiography. Gardner died in San Diego on January 5th, 1992.
Chronology
June 27, 1904: Born in Sallisaw, Oklahoma. Has two older sisters, Gertrude Miller and Catherine Carson.
1910: Mother dies when she was 10 years old.
1921 to 1924: Attended University of Missouri, graduated with a Bachelor of Journalism.
Dec. 17, 1927: Married Jerome Butler, a socialist newspaperman and copy reader
1927: Employed at the St. Louis Times.
May 1927: Father dies.
1929: Hired by Chicago Tribune.
July, 1937: Married Marion (Red) Marberry whom she described as a leftist who never joined the Party. He was also a newspaperman and wrote three books:Joaquin Miller American Poet (1953); Vicky: A Biography of Victoria Woodhull (1967); The Golden Voice: A Biography of Isaac Kelloch (1947).
September, 1937:"Decided to join the Communist Party."
April, 1938: Joined the Newspaper Guild in Chicago.
1938: Active in Hearst strike in California.
1939: Joined the Communist Party.
1939: Filed charges with the National Labor Relations Board regarding unfair treatment at Chicago Tribune.
1939: Assisted in publishing the Tribunit, a publication of the Chicago Tribune workers.
March 22, 1940: Dismissed from Chicago Tribune, because of involvement in Guild activities at the paper.
1940: Moved to New York where she worked with the Women's Division of the Democratic National Committee.
1941: Voted as lifetime member of the Newspaper Guild.
1941: Acted as Executive Secretary of the Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges (President of the ILWU),in New York City in an attempt to prevent his deportation from the United States.
1942: Moved to Washington D.C.; Divorced Marion (Red) Marberry (January); Begins work at Federated Press, a labor news service; serves as Executive Secretary to the American Council on Soviet Relations, a precursor to the National Council of American Soviet Friendship (NCASF).
1943: Resigned from Federated Press. Began working as Washington correspondent for New Masses.
1947: Resigned from New Masses, and moved to Los Angeles; where she began working for The Peoples World
1948: Subpoenaed to appear before the Tenney Committee (California's Fact-Finding Committee on Un-American Activities).
1949: Wrote a few articles for Masses and Mainstream.
1951: Dismissed from The Peoples World.
1952: Moved back to New York; employed in Jamaica, Queens in a meat packing plant.
1954: The Rosenberg Story, published by Masses and Mainstream.
1955: Began work at the Daily Worker.
December 1959: Resigned from the Worker.
Feb.-June 1960: Worked on staff of Factor, a monthly magazine which covers issues related to psychiatry.
1960 to 1962: Freelanced as a medical writer.
1962: Left the Communist Party.
1963 to 1971: Employed as editorial assistant to Corliss Lamont.
1982: Published Friend and Lover, a biography of Louise Bryant (New York:
1984 to 1989: Worked on her unpublished autobiography.
1989: Grandson, John Dorney dies; in failing health.
1992: Dies in San Diego, January 5th.
Scope and Content Note
Series I. Autobiography contains a lengthy and rather personal unpublished untitled autobiographical typescript, related correspondence, and a genealogy and other biographical materials.
Series II. Correspondence is divided into personal (family and friends) and political correspondence and spans the years 1922 to 1990. Personal correspondents include her son John Marberry, her nephew John Gardner, several friends, and boyfriends Brady Pryor, Dud Jarret, Paul Cawthron, Andy Anderson, John McShane, and Milt Rogart and his wife. The political correspondence is with communists, other radicals and several well-known writers, including Bill Allen, Sender A. Garlin, Ammon Hennacy, Corrine Hardesty, Corliss Lamont, Kay Hall Sessions, Frank Spector, John Tessitore, Nick Unger, Harry and Nikki Bridges and William Appleman Williams.
Series III. Political Activities, is divided into two sections: A. General, which contains files on the Rosenberg case, the American Council on Soviet Relations, and Gardner's testimony before various legislative committees; and B. The Harry Bridges Case, which contains clippings, correspondence between Gardner and Harry and Nikki Bridges, and Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges materials related to the campaign to prevent his deportation from the United States.
Series IV. Journalism Career, consists of five chronologically arranged subseries that represent the different newspapers and the various cities in which she lived and worked, and which primarily contain copies of Gardner's articles, and correspondence. The subseries and employment/residence dates are: A. Chicago Tribune(1930-1941); B. Federated Press (Washington D.C., 1942-1943); C. New Masses(Washington D.C., 1943-1947); D. Los Angeles (1947-1952), Peoples World; E. New York (1952-1980s), Daily Worker and after.
Series V. Correspondence Addendum. Consists of correspondence from the 1970s and 1980s.
Series VI. Research Files. The files for Friend and Lover consists of Gardner's extensive and unusually rich research files for her biography of Louise Bryant. Contents include clippings, correspondence and interviews with prominent friends and associates, ephemera, primary source documents including a copy of Bryant's marriage license (to John Reed), and a typescript of the book. The Rosenberg Story Research Files contain clippings and other ephemera.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: I. Autobiography; II. Correspondence; III. Political Activities; IV. Journalism Career; V. Correspondence Addendum; VI. Research Files.
Folders are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically based on the nature of the series.
Allen, Bill, 1914-; American Council on Soviet Relations.; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Bridges, Nikki; Bryant, Louise, 1885-1936; Chicago Tribune (Firm).; Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Daily Worker (New York).; Gardner, John.; Gardner, Virginia. Friend and lover.; Gardner, Virginia. Rosenberg story.; Gardner, Virginia.; Garlin, Sender A.; Hardesty, Corrine.; Hennacy, Ammon, 1893-1970; Hilliard, Noel; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995.; Masses & mainstream.; McGrath, Thomas, 1916-1990.; Newspaper Guild.; People's world (San Francisco, Calif.).; Richmond, Al, 1913-1987.; Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953; Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953; Sessions, Kay Hall.; Spector, Frank.; Tessitore, John.; Unger, Nick; Williams, William Appleman; Articles.; Autobiography (genre).; Biography (genre).; Birth certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Collective bargaining |x Journalists |z Illinois |z Chicago.; Communists |z United States; Correspondence.; Death certificates.; Files (document groupings); Interviews.; Journalism, Communist--United States.; Newspaper columns.; Single mothers |z United States.; Typescripts.; United States |x Foreign relations |z Soviet Union.; Women communists |z United States.; Women journalists--United States.
- Series I: Autobiography
  - Subseries I:A: Personal data documents.
    - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence seeking residency at Renwick Gardens., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Genealogy, 1954-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Insurance Book, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Misc. personals., 1922-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Personal Data, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Photoprints, 1951-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Photoprint copy of 50th Reunion of Fort Smith Class, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Wills, etc., 1968-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries I:B: Autobiography.
    - A Summary, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chapter Plan, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - John Tessitore's copy with his comments., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 1 -Other Singular Lives, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2 -Life at Columbia Missouri., undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 3 -Saskatchewan., undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 4 -Pawhuska., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 5 -From Fort Smith to Kansas City., undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 6 -Father., undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 7 -Depression., undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 8 -Dr. Gerty., undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 9 -Red and I Marry., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 10-Red Joins The Picketline., undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 11 -John is Born., undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 12 -A Stupid Business., undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 13 -I Got Sold Down The River., undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 14 -The Letter Bridges Pocketed., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 15 -Father and Son., undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 16 -Back to Reporting., undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 17 -An Exciting Visitor., undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 18 -New Friends and Old., undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 19 -I Learn a Lesson, or 1 or 2., undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 20 -Criticism and SelfCriticism., undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 21 -Back to New York., undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 22 -Not the Best of Years., undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 23 -Julius and Ethel Rosenberg., undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - 24 -Milt Again., undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Subseries I:C: Correspondence re Autobiography.
    - Carrol, Joe, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Cohen, Hy (Publisher), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Gerty, Dr. (Psychiatrist), 1964-1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Pashe, Vic, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Re: publication of autobiography, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Richmond, Al, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Stevens, Don, 1940-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries II:A: Correspondence with relatives.
    - Carson, Catherine, 1933-1984 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Carson, Catherine - Newspaper article re: her novel, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Dorney, John, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Dorney, John - death, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Gardner, Carolyn, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Gardner, Carolyn: Newspaper article re death of, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Gardner, John (VG's nephew), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Marberry, John (VG's son), 1947-1984 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Marberry, John and family photoprints (photocopies of), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Marberry, Red (Marion) - John's father, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Marberry Relatives, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Miller, Gertrude, 1929-1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Miller, Gertrude Miller - burial of, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - G.R. Wood of the Above Ground Review, discusses John Gardner, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Misc. from relatives, 1930-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Misc. notes and correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Misc. notes and correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II:B: Correspondence with close friends
    - Anderson, Brady, 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cawthron, Paul and Dud Jarret, 1923-1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Frank, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Gauldin, Sara, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Gauldin, Sara - on the Manuscript of Louise Bryant, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Gauldin, Sara - Poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - McShane, John, 1935-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pryor, Brady, 1922-1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Rogart, Milt (see chapter 24 of autobiography), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Rogart, Pat (Milt's wife), 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Sullivan, Nancy, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - VG's copies of outgoing correspondence, 1946-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subseries II:C: Political correspondence
    - Abrowitz, Murray - M.D., 1964-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Allen, Bill, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Coleman, Louis (Limey), 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Coover, Robert, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Garlin, Sender A., 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Garrigue, Jean - Poet, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Grossner, Isabel, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hardesty, Corrine, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Hennacy, Ammon, 1958-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Hillard, Noel, 1954-1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Hillard, Noel, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Lamont, Corliss - regarding his autobiography, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lindsay, Vina, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Marzani, Carl - Regarding trial of, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - McGrath, Tom, 1956-1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Murray, George and Virginia, 1972-1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Harvey O'Conner, Harvey - obituary, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Richmond, Al, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Rosemary, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Segure, Rose, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Sessions, Kay Hall, 1962-1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Spector, Frank, 1951-1985 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Stone, Jack and Bert Stone, (Jack edited On The WashingtonRecord, copy of volume I, June 27, 1965, is included, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Tessitore, John A., 1981-1989 (Folder 42)
    - Under, Nick, 1971 (Folder 43)
    - Williams, William Appleman, 1966-1967 (Folder 44)
- Series III: Political Activities
  - Subseries III:A: Political activities
    - VG's statement before Senate Judicial Committee regarding Francis Biddle's nomination as U.S. Attorney General., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - American Council on Soviet Relations, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - American Council on Soviet Relations, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - VG's annotated copy of Party Voice, V.II, #6, September to October 1954., undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - VG and the Tenney UnAmerican Committee, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Political Beefs, 1955-1976 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - News Release to Moscow Tass and Sovietskaya Kultura, regarding death of Fred Ellis., 1965 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - News release from, New York StateCommunist Party, State Committee, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Misc. apparently from Party Members, 1959-1970 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Related to publication in Catholic Digest of "Labority Within Cloistered Walls," 1961. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - National Committee to Reopen Rosenberg Case, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Unidentified, but related to a Congressional Committee Hearing, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Misc., 1928-1990 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Subseries III:B: Harry Bridges Case.
    - Findings and Conclusion of the Trial Examination in the Matter of Harry Bridges, a publication of the U.S. Government Printing Office, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings and Brief by Lawyers Guild on Harry Bridges Case, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - ILWU Handbook in recognition of Harry Bridges, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Releases from Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper clippings on Harry Bridges Case, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings on Harry Bridges Case, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Auditors Report on Citizens Committee for Harry Bridges and other correspondence related to his deportation, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper articles on Harry Bridges Case, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Harry Bridges letter to Citizens Committee and VGM, 1942-1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Lawyers Guild to President of the U.S. requesting cancellation of Harry Bridges deportation, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence between VGM and Harry and Nikki Bridges, includes newspaper clippings, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Journalism Career
  - Subseries IV:A: Chicago Tribune
    - Chicago Tribune Newspaper articles by VG, 1930-1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Misc. correspondence and research materials while at the Chicago Tribune, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Tribune correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Photocopy of 12/25/38 Picture Section of Chicago Tribune includes a picture OF VG, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence:Don Max, possibly Tribune related, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Tribune manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Photocopy Chicago Sunday Tribune cover page, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Disposed. Same as Folder # 15 in this Series., undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tribune stories by VG, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Disposed.Same as Folder # 18 in this series., undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence regarding Tribune firing, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - settlement of VG's Tribune case, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Tribune articles by VG, 1930-1938 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Tribune Documents, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Photocopies of photoprints "Signing of Hearst Chain Peace Formula" ending Chicago strike., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence:Guild activities at The Tribune, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Copies of the Tribunit, Guild newspaper of the Chicago Tribune workers, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence: Newspaper Guild of New York and Chicago, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - St. Louis Newspaper Guild Newsletter, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Union Songs by Chicago Newspaper Guild, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Guild activities and songs., undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Eulogy for Morgan Hull of Los Angeles Newspaper Guild, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Subseries IV:B: Federated Press, Washington D.C.
    - Political hassles at Federated Press, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Federated Press articles by VG, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Federated Press articles by VG, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Letter of resignation, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence and Union Leader, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence: Job related, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Subseries IV:C: New Masses, Washington D.C.
    - New Masses:Articles by VG, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - New Masses: Articles by VG, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Subseries IV:D: California employment
    - Peoples Voice; New Masses:Articles by VG, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Challenge Newspaper: Articles by VG, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence: Regarding Councilman Davenport's anti- communist attack and Los Angeles Fire and Police article, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Peoples World speech in San Francisco fundraising effort, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence:Masses and Mainstream, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Newspaper article by VG in Daily Peoples World, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Newspaper article by VG in Daily Peoples World on Terminal Island, in Our World newspaper, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Daily Peoples World: Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Peoples World:Articles by VG and correspondence, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - VG's case from California Review Committee, regarding Peoples World employment, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - On getting fired by Slim, correspondence etc. from Peoples World employment, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Political notes to self on Slim Meeting, undated (Folder 54)
    - Peoples World staff meeting speech by VG, undated (Folder 55)
  - Subseries IV:E: New York employment
    - Daily Worker article by VG "Is this the answer to a tenant prayer.", 1955 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Newspaper article by VG in the Worker, includes notes, 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Notes on Daily Worker articles, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Correspondence: Ben Levine, " Daily Worker Unsung Hero,", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Daily Peoples World and Daily Worker articles by VG, 1948-1957 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Daily Worker Radium Story by VG, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Articles by VG, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence from Charles Headly to Daily Worker editor, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Articles by VG while at Chicago Tribune, Federated Press, and Daily Worker, 1930-1957 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence to editor, Party Voice, Party Affairs,and Daily Worker, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Newspaper articles by VG in the Worker, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Correspondence regarding VG's article in Science and Society, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)